[音乐]
[MUSIC]
&gt；&gt；Douglas Crockford：所以，我一直在考虑下一种语言。
&gt;&gt; Douglas Crockford: So, I've been thinking a lot about the next language.
什么语言取代了JavaScript和
What's the language that replaces JavaScript and
我真的希望有一种新的语言。
I really hope there is a next language.
因为如果JavaScript是最后一种编程语言，
Because if JavaScript is the last programming language,
那真的很可悲。
that would be really sad.
不是吗？
Wouldn't it?
我的意思是，对我们的孩子来说，对，我们需要给他们留下一种更好的语言。
I mean, for our kids, right,we need to leave them a better language.
我们不能让JavaScript成为最后一种语言。
We can't allow JavaScript to be the last language.
所以一定要有什么东西来继承它
So something is going to have to have to succeed it and
我一直在寻找下一种语言，有什么迹象？
I've been searching for the next language, and what are the signs?
我们怎么知道它在这里？
How will we know when it's here?
这有点像等待弥赛亚，你怎么知道的？
And it's sort of like waiting the Messiah, how do you know?
我不知道，但我正在寻找
And I don't know, but I'm looking for and
然后我开始试着去理解它将会是什么。
then I'm starting to try to understand what it's going to be.
我很有信心，它还没有到。
I'm confident, it's not here yet.
实际上，我不知道。
Actually, I don't know that.
它可能就在这里，但我只是还没有意识到它，但是
It might be it's here, but I just haven't recognized it yet, but
有人告诉我，这是C#。
there are people who tell me, it C#.
不，不。
No, no, no.
或者是Java，它一直都在这里，不。
Or it's Java, it's been here the whole time, no, no.
下一种语言是另一种语言，这就是事情，
The next language is another language and it's the thing,
这是取代JavaScript的正确方法，但我们还没有看到它。
which is the right thing to replace JavaScript and we haven't seen it yet.
但我想了很多关于它将会是什么以及它将会做什么。
But I think a lot about what it's going to be and what it's going to do.
我相信，当它到来时，我们将一如既往地立即拒绝它
I am confident that when it arrives, we will reject it out of hand, as we always
这样做，因为程序员和普通人一样情绪化和非理性。
do, because programmers are as emotional and irrational as normal people.
我们认为我们不是，也许我们的配偶告诉我们不是，但这是真的。
We think that we're not and maybe our spouses tell us we're not, but it's true.
我们是，我们对我们所做的事情的大部分想法都是基于情感，并且
We are and most of what we think about what we do is based on emotion, and
不是理性的，即使我们想象它是另一种方式。
not on reason, even though we imagine it's the other way around.
所以这听起来像是对我自己职业的疯狂指控，但我有一些
So this sounds like a wild charge to make of my own profession, but I have some
这么说有很好的理由，我认为历史记录支持我这一点。
good reasons for saying this and I think the historical record backs me up on this.
例如，
For example,
花了一代人的时间才同意高级语言是个好主意。
it took a generation to agree that high-level languages were a good idea.
回到早期，那时一切都是用汇编语言和
Back in the early days when everything was in assembly language and
第一批高级语言正在开发中，如Fortran、COBOL等。
the first high-level languages were being developed, Fortran, COBOL and so on.
谁会从这些语言的使用中获益最多？
Who would have most benefited from use of those languages?
程序员。
The programmers.
反对那些语言的人是谁？
Who was it who was opposed to those languages?
是程序员。
It was the programmers.
他们抱怨语言正在夺走他们的控制权。
They were complaining that the languages were taking control away from them.
他们没有给他们所需要的表演。
That they didn't give them the performance that they needed.
他们之所以想要呆在烂摊子里是有这些原因的，他们
They had all these reasons for why they wanted to stay down in the muck, that they
不想在这些更有表现力，更有生产力的语言中得到提升。
didn't want to be elevated in these more expressive, productive languages.
花了一代人的时间才同意后藤健二是个坏主意。
It took a generation to agree that goto was a bad idea.
他在67年发表了他的信，这引发了一场争论，
Publishes his letter in 67 and that starts an argument,
这真的持续了20年，所有的争论都是愚蠢的争论。
that literally goes on for 20 years and the arguments were all silly arguments.
现在，我们需要Goto的表现。
Now, we need the performance of the goto.
这是我表达自己的方式。
It's how I express myself.
如果我不能使用Goto，我就不能做我自己。
I can't be me, if I can't use goto.
我们有一个goto传统，我祖父用goto。
We have a goto tradition, my grandfather used goto.
你不能拿我冰冷的死手，所有那些争论都是关于后藤的。
You can't take my cold dead hand, all of those arguments were all made about goto.
花了一代人的时间才同意物件是个好主意。
It took a generation to agree that objects were a good idea.
所以物体是1967年在挪威的Simula首次发现的-
So objects are first discovered in Simula in Norway in 1967-
&gt；&gt；扬声器2：在冰下。
&gt;&gt; Speaker 2: Under the ice.
&GT；&GT；道格拉斯·克罗克福德：对不起。&gt；&gt；扬声器2：在冰下。
&gt;&gt; Douglas Crockford: I'm sorry. &gt;&gt; Speaker 2: Under the ice.
你说，他们被发现了。
You said, they were discovered.
&gt；&gt；Douglas Crockford：嗯，在挪威。
&gt;&gt; Douglas Crockford: Well, in Norway.
&gt；&gt；扬声器2：在冰下。
&gt;&gt; Speaker 2: Under the ice.
&gt；&gt；Douglas Crockford：不，在奥斯陆。
&gt;&gt; Douglas Crockford: No, in Oslo.
就像所有真正重要的创新一样，
And as always happens with the really important innovations,
世界根本没有注意到，除了一个人，
the world took no notice at all, except for one guy,
犹他州大学的研究生艾伦·凯。
a graduate student at the University of Utah, Alan Kay.
然后，他把这个想法带到加州的施乐帕洛阿尔托研究中心(Xerox Parc)，
Who then takes this idea to Xerox PARC in California,
认为这个物体的概念是这样的
thinking that this idea of objects is so
令人难以置信的强大，他可以使用它作为儿童的编程语言。
incredibly powerful that he can use it as a programming language for children.
孩子们可以用它来编程他们的个人便携设备。
That children can use to program their personal portable devices.
他有很多远见，这是对的。
There was a lot of his vision, which was right.
他的很多愿景我们还没有赶上，
A lot of his vision we haven't caught up to yet,
我们仍然没有适合儿童的语言。
we still don't have the language for children.
我认为我们还没有一种适合成年人的语言，但我们仍在努力，
I don't think we have a language for adults yet, but we're still working on it,
但后来他们花了十年的时间开发这种语言
but they then spent a decade developing that language and
在这方面做了非常出色的工作。
did a brilliant, brilliant job on it.
因此，在80年代末，该行业有一个选择。
And so in the late 80s, the industry had a choice.
我们将进入面向对象编程。
We're gonna go into object oriented programming.
花了很长时间才到那里，但我们会做到的。
It took a long time to get there, but we're gonna do it.
我们是不是要用Smalltalk-80，最好的设计之一
Are we gonna go with Smalltalk-80, one of the best designed
历史上的编程语言，还是我们要用C+？
programming languages in history, or are we gonna go with C++?
做出这个决定的人根本不明白
And the decision was made by people who fundamentally did not understand
面向对象编程，他们选择了C+。
object-oriented programming and they chose C++.
因为为了使用这种语言，
Because in order to use that language,
您不需要了解任何有关面向对象编程的内容。
you did not need to understand anything about object oriented programming.
这种语言在对象系统方面有一些根本错误。
That language got some things fundamentally wrong about object systems.
不幸的是，这种语言极具影响力
Unfortunately, the language has been extremely influential and
为此后发生的一切奠定了基础。
has set the mold for virtually everything that's happened ever since.
我不知道你能不能赶上Smalltalk，
I don't know if are ever going to catch up to Smalltalk,
然后两代人才同意lambdas是个好主意。
then it took two generations to agree that lambdas were a good idea.
所以，Alan Kay是一个Smalltalk的人，他从写作开始
So, Alan Kay who is a Smalltalk guy, he started by writing
在Data General Mini计算机上用Nova Basic编写的一个小程序，它
a little program in NOVA basic on a Data General Mini Computer, which
展示了他奇怪的小语言，他开始带着这个想法巡回演出。
demonstrated his weird little language, and he started touring with this idea.
把它带到实验室和大学，他参观了麻省理工学院。
Taking it to labs and universities, and he visited MIT.
麻省理工学院的非常聪明的人，他告诉他们他的新语言，但是
Very smart guys at MIT and he's telling them about his new language, but
它仍然是早期的对象去编程和
it's still early in object going to programming and
他没有我们现在所拥有的词汇来描述正在发生的事情。
he doesn't have the vocabulary that we have now to describe what's going on.
所以他不能说你在一个对象上调用了一个方法，
So he couldn't say you invoke a method on an object,
因为还没有人知道要这么说。
cuz nobody knew to say that yet.
因此，他描述了它，当你向一个对象发送消息时。
So he described it, as you send a message to an object.
嗯，麻省理工学院的人听他说，好吧，你不是真的发送
Well, the guys at MIT listening to him say, well, you're not actually sending
一条信息，你正在做一个方向内的子程序指示。
a message, you're making a sub routine indication within direction.
但如果你真的发出了信息呢？
But what if you did send a message?
这就开始了对演员模型和演员模型的研究，
And that started research in the actor model and the actor model,
实际上，这些实体在不同的系统中运行
you actually have these entities that are running in separate systems
可以互相发送信息。
that can send messages to each other.
这基本上就是演员和想出这个主意的人，
That's basically what actors are and the guy who came up with this,
卡尔·休伊特(Carl Hewitt)就是其中之一，他非常聪明。
Carl Hewitt, is one of these guys who's so amazingly smart.
就像他出生在范式转变的另一边。
It's like he was born on the other side of the paradigm shift.
当他谈论东西的时候，人们听不懂他在说什么。
When he talks about stuff, people cannot understand what he's saying.
他很清楚，他很有口才，他说得真的很好，但是
He's very clear, he's very eloquent, he speaks really well, but
他是从一个参照系里说的，这就是
he's talking from a frame of reference, which is so
对其他人类来说没有人能理解他。
foreign to the rest of humanity that nobody understands him.
包括麻省理工学院的其他人，他们都非常聪明
Including the other people at MIT, they were all very smart and
他们都很尊重卡尔，但是
they all had a lot of respect for Carl, but
他们搞不懂他对所有这些演员都在说些什么。
they couldn't figure out what he was raving about with all these actors.
因此，他们中的一对，苏斯曼和斯蒂尔，决定我们需要建造一些有序的东西
So a couple of them, Sussman and Steele, decide we need to build something in order
去理解卡尔说的是什么。
to understand what it is that Carl's talking about.
因此，他们首先采用LISP并将其重写为一种语言，该语言
So they start by taking LISP and rewriting it into a language which
对参与者模型进行建模，并且他们没有完全实现参与者模型。
models the actor model, and they didn't fully implement the actor model.
所以他们从来没有弄明白，但是他们创造的语言
So they never did figure it out, but the language that they created
被称为计划，他们意外地发现
was called Scheme and they had accidentally discovered
带有词法闭包的函数和我们今天一直在做的所有东西。
functions with lexical closure and all the stuff that we've been working on today.
所以，事实上你可以有更高阶的函数，
So, the fact that you could have higher order functions,
返回函数的函数以及所有意外发生的事情，
functions that return functions and all that stuff happened happened by accident,
试图弄清楚卡尔·休伊特在说什么。
trying to figure out what Carl Hewitt was talking about.
这可能是编程史上最重要的发现。
And that is maybe the most important discovery in the history of programming.
就像经常发生的那样，世界根本没有注意到这一点
And as always happens, the world took no notice of it at all and
它只是在麻省理工学院闲坐了很多年，没有任何进展，只是现在，
it just sat around at MIT for years and years going nowhere and is only now,
终于过了40年，终于走进了主流。
finally after 40 years, finally coming to the mainstream.
它正在成为主流，因为它实际上是一个非常好的想法
And it's coming to the mainstream, because it was actually a really good idea and
它的时候到了。
its time has come.
我们现在真的很需要它。
We really need it now.
所以这些事情花了这么长时间的原因，
So the reason these things take so long,
每件事至少需要一代人的时间，因为我们不会改变主意。
everything takes at least a generation, is because we don't change minds.
我们必须等待一代人退休或死亡之前
We have to wait for a generation to retire or die before
我们可以在下一个新想法上获得临界质量，这就是进展的方式。
we can get critical mass on the next new idea and that's the way progress goes.
我们认为这是一个极具创新性的行业，在某些方面确实如此，但是
We imagine this is an extremely innovative industry, and in some ways it is, but
在某些方面，我们和其他人一样。
in some ways, we're just like everybody else.
所以，我经历了Goto的事情。
So, I lived through the goto thing.
我记得当时发生的事情和所有的争论，他们真的
I remember when that was happening and all the arguments, and they were really
情绪愤怒的争论，而所有的争论都来自情感。
emotional angry arguments, and all the arguments were from emotion.
很少有来自事实的争论
There was very little argument from fact and
它只是继续，然后它变得安静。
it just went on, and on, and on, and on, and then it got quiet.
就像是，他们走了吗？
It was like, are they gone?
我们现在可以摆脱Goto了吗？
Can we get rid of the goto now?
我们做到了，我们摆脱了它，它不见了。
And we did, we got rid of it and it's gone.
我们不会错过所有的承诺
And we're not missing it and all of the promises
世界末日即将来临，如果我们除掉Goto或者
that the world was going to end, if we took rid of goto or
程序员的生活将变得更加悲惨。
the lives of programmers are gonna be made more miserable.
这些都不是真的，我们没有错过。
None of that turned out to be true, we're not missing it.
没有它我们做得很好。
We're doing great without it.
事实上，我们的一些语言可能有一点太多的Goto留在他们，
In fact, some of our languages have maybe a little bit too much goto left in them,
但我们还过得去。
but we're getting by.
所以，事实证明我们从来都不需要Goto。
So, it turns out we never needed goto.
不需要。
Don't need it.
没有它我们做得更好。
We're doing better without it.
事实上，真正发生的是摆脱了后藤，
And in fact, what actually happened was by getting rid of goto,
它使编写更复杂的程序变得更容易。
it made it easier to write programs of greater complexity.
因为如果您唯一的控制结构是GOTO和条件GOTO，
Because if your only control construct is goto and conditional goto,
在程序变得无法管理之前，程序的复杂程度是有限的。
there's a limit to how complex a program can get before it comes unmanageable.
通过去掉Goto，我们可以在更大的程序中做得更好
And by getting rid of goto, we could do better with larger programs and
我们可以在编写软件方面更好地实现我们的雄心壮志。
we could do better at achieving our ambitions in terms of writing software.
所以，反对后藤的人就是那些
So, the people who are arguing against goto were the people who would have
受益于Goto。
benefited from goto.
他们从摆脱Goto中受益，而且总是这样，而且
They're benefited from getting rid of goto and it is always like that, and
我希望永远都是这样。
I expect it will always be like that.
所以在寻找下一种语言时，我希望它能有所不同
So in looking for the next language, I'm looking for it to be different in
一些重要的方式，我希望它会因为这些差异而被钉在十字架上。
some important ways and I'm expecting it to be crucified for those differences.